when a farmer in new south wales
australia discovered a large black
object sticking out of the ground in a
remote part of his land he thought it
was a tree
but this turned out to be a piece of
space junk which had fallen from the sky
the australian space agency later said
it came from a spacex capsule dr brad
tucker is an astrophysicist at the
australian national university and he
was called to examine the object
a lot of people often think they find
space chunk of meteorites and it's
always exciting to hear but
usually easy to determine it's not in
something more earthly but in this case
when we got the call we also knew this
that previously a couple weeks prior the
trunk of the spacex crew one capsule had
re-entered over the area in australia
and at that time lots of people saw it
breaking apart they heard sonic booms
and the place the farmers were calling
from was smack underneath that path so i
was like hey this actually may be junk
and then when i saw the photos
you clearly saw that there was something
weird about this so it was an exciting
call to some degree to go and hop in in
the car and drive relatively nearby a
few hours uh to go investigate and
confirm that this was indeed space junk
from the spacex crew one uh trunk
capsule usually when we have reports of
space junk it's hard to figure out the
source because there could be so many
different things in this case because
that part was so well cataloged and it
was so well observed entering the
atmosphere and fragmenting and breaking
apart we kind of knew that this had
happened and once we were able to get
the location and then obviously go there
firstly it was making sure well how
exactly close is this bought to that
flight path and it was within you know a
few kilometers which is as good as you
get
you can also then see subtleties in the
way it's made so in fact we are looking
at the scorching patterns as this junk
hits the earth's atmosphere it breaks
apart but due to the massive friction of
the atmosphere causes bits of it to burn
and essentially incinerate which you can
see you can then also see the materials
that it was made up of uh to confirm you
know this indeed is high-tech
manufacturing and not
farm equipment laying down so to speak
and the benefit here which was the final
part was there's part numbers on it very
rarely do you get the part numbers
labeled
and this allowed us to uh
confidently say it was from this and
actually then reach out to spacex who
then also confirmed that it was indeed
theirs